Lalage J. Bown Papers
Lalage J. Bown Papers
1961-1980
1971-1979
Bown, Lalage J.
3.5 linear ft.
Papers of the Oxford-educated professor of adult education. Bown spent much of her professional career in Africa, establishing adult education programs at various universities in Ghana, Uganda, and Nigeria. The collection includes organizational materials, correspondence, papers and printed material relating to adult education in Africa, Hong Kong, India and the West Indies. Bulk of material from the African Adult Education Association, Nigerian National Council for Adult Education and UNESCO.
149312
Biographical History
Lalage J. Bown was born in Surrey, U.K. in 1927 but spent much of her professional career in Africa, establishing or expanding adult education programs at various universities in Ghana, Uganda, and Nigeria. She attended Cheltenham Ladies' College and the University of Oxford, where she took Second Class Honors in Modern History (1949) and then continued on to an M.A. (1952). She taught briefly at the University of Edinburgh before relocating to Africa where she taught at the University College of the Gold Coast, Ghana; Makerere University College, Uganda; University of Ibadan, Nigeria; University of Zambia; Ahmadu Bello University, Nigeria; and the University of Lagos. In most of these positions, she was involved in either establishing or substantially enhancing Adult Education and extension programs and/or departments. She also directed or chaired various short-term programs including an 8-week Peace Corps training program at the University of California, a Carnegie Foundation training program for African diplomats, and a seminar for diplomats working in London.
She was involved in many programs for teaching African literature and arts in the various parts of Nigeria, and among other things in the organization of the first-ever conference on African culture to be held on African soil. She was also the first organizing secretary of the International Congress of Africanists. Her book Two Centuries of African English (Heinemann, 1973) arose directly from efforts to Africanize the curriculum, both in formal education and in the wider community.
In 1975 she was awarded an honorary doctorate from Open University "for services to the education of the underprivileged," and the William Pearson Tolley Award from Syracuse University, the first woman to receive this award. In 1981 she returned to the U.K., accepting a position with the Department of Adult and Continuing Education at the University of Glasgow. In 2002 that institution awarded her an Honorary Doctor of Letters (D.Litt.).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Lalage J. Bown Papers primarily contains material related to conferences, seminars and workshops held by various adult education organizations in Africa. There is also printed material relating to adult and continuing education programs at various colleges and universities in Africa, Hong Kong, India and the West Indies; various issues of African adult education journals and newsletters, and a few photographs (unidentified). The bulk of the material dates from 1971-1979.
Biographical information includes a c.v. from 1979. Associations comprises folders of constitutions, resolutions and other informational documents of various organizations. Conferences contains proceedings and other matter related to various conferences and is organized alphabetically, as are the Meetings, Seminars, and Workshops series. Printed material includes informational material on colleges, universities, and adult education programs in Africa, Hong Kong, India and the West Indies, followed by miscellaneous printed material in alphabetical order.
The following organizations are heavily represented: African Adult Education Association (formerly the Adult Education Association of East and Central Africa, AEAECA); Distance Education Association of Southern Africa (formerly the Botswana, Lesotho, Swaziland Correspondence Committee); International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE); Nigerian National Council for Adult Education (NNCAE); and the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO).
Individuals represented (usually by conference presentation or paper) include A.A. Ali, S.B. Allen, William Cave, J.E. Chilipweli, S. Cooppan, David Crowley, P.O.H. Dada, O.L. Farrag, Soloman Inquai, J.H. Mwanakatwe, A.H. Nasution, J.T. Okedara, J. Paulus, E.A. Tugbiyele, Abdelwahid A. Yousif.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Allen, S. R.; Bown, Lalage J.; Cave, William M.; Chilipweli, J. E.; Cooppan, S. (Somarsundarum); Crowley, David.; Inquai, Solomon.; Nasution, Amir H.; Tugbiyele, E. A.; Yousif, Abdelwahid Abdalla.; Adult Education Association of East and Central Africa.; African Adult Education Association.; Botswana Lesotho Swaziland Correspondence Committee.; Distance Education Association of Southern Africa.; International Congress of University Adult Education.; Nigerian National Council for Adult Education.; Unesco; Adult education -- Africa.; Adult education -- China -- Hong Kong.; Adult education -- India.; Adult education -- West Indies.; Adult educators -- Training of.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Newsletters.; Notes (documents); Pamphlets.; Papers (document genres); Adult educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Lalage J. Bown.
Inventory
- Biographical information
  - Curriculum vitae, 1979 (Box 1)
- Associations
  - Adult Education Association of East and Central Africa (AEAECA) (Box 1)
    See also African Adult Education Association (AAEA).
  - African Adult Education Association (AAEA), resolutions, constitution, accounts (Box 1)
    See also Adult Education Association of East and Central Africa (AEAECA); Printed material: African Adult Education Association (AAEA).
  - Botswana, Lesotho, Swaziland Correspondence Committee, meeting minutes, newsletters (Box 1)
  - Nigerian National Council for Adult Education (NNCAE), resolutions, constitution, accounts, organization (Box 1)
    See also Printed material: Nigerian National Council for Adult Education (NNCAE).
- Conferences
  - Adult Education Association of East and Central Africa (AEAECA), Jan 1968 (Box 1)
  - African Adult Education Association (AAEA)
    - 3rd conference, Apr 1971; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 4th conference, Sep 1973; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 6th conference, 27 Feb - 4 Mar 1978; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Annual Conference/Seminar of Heads of Adult Education Departments in the State Ministries and Universities, 24 Jun - 28 Jun 1980 (Box 2)
  - Chief Community Development Officers, University Lecturers and Students of AMTC Conference, 13 Jan - 3 Feb 1973 (Box 2)
  - Conference on Adult Education in Africa, 28 Dec 1961 - 6 Jan 1962 (Box 2)
  - Conference/Seminar of Heads of Adult Education Sections/Departments in the State Ministries and Universities, 4-6 Oct 1978 (Box 2)
  - Nigerian National Council for Adult Education (NNCAE)
    - 1st conference, 4th executive meeting, 2d general meeting, Mar 1972 (Box 2)
    - 4th conference, Jul 1975 (Box 2)
    - 5th conference and seminar, 4th general meeting, Jul 1976 (Box 2)
    - 8th conference and seminar, Jul 1979 (Box 2)
- Meetings
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Adult Education: I.I.T.A. (Box 3)
  - AAEA
    - Executive Committee Meeting, 5 Aug 1968 (Box 3)
    - 4th General Meeting, 14 Sep 1973 (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee Meeting, 26-27 Feb 1978 (Box 3)
    - 6th General Meeting, 2-3 Mar 1978 (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee Meeting, 28 Jun 1976 (Box 3)
    - Working Party Meeting, 26-27 Feb 1977 (Box 3)
    - Management and Programme Committee Meeting, 14-15 Apr 1978 (Box 3)
  - Ahmadu Bello University, Adult Education and General Extension Services Unit, staff meetings, 30 Oct 1973; 1 Nov 1973 (Box 3)
  - Audio-Visual Advisory Committee, 15th meeting, 2 Nov 1973 (Box 3)
  - International Congress of University Adult Educatio, 1st Regional Meeting, 1971 (Box 3)
  - NNCAE 14th Executive Committee Meeting, 4th General Meeting, 1975 (Box 3)
  - UNESCO
    - Meeting of Experts on Comparative Adult Education (2d International ), 1975 (Box 3)
    - Meeting of Experts on Post-Literacy, 25 Arp - 30 Apr 1977 (Box 3)
    - Meeting of Experts to Review the International Standard Classification of Education (ISCED), Dec 1974 (Box 3)
    - Meeting of Experts on the Use of Mother Tongues in Literacy Programmes in Africa, 30 Sep - 4 Oct 1977 (Box 3)
- Seminars
  - Bauchi State Seminar/Workshop for Adult Educators and Practitioners in Related Disciplines (Nigeria), 5-7 Dec 1978 (Box 4)
  - Centre for Cultural Studies, University of Lagos, Nigeria, "The Interrelationship of Art", 12-18 Feb 1978 (Box 4)
  - Commonwealth Secretariat, University of Manchester, "Commonwealth Seminar on Adult Educational and National Development", 11-16 Oct 1972 (Box 4)
  - UNESCO, "Structure of Adult Education in Developing Countries", 1975 (Box 4)
  - University of Edinburgh Centre for African Studies - "Education and Community in Africa, 18-20 Jun 1976 (Box 4)
- Workshops
  - Adult Education Association of East and Central Africa - adult education workshop, 12 Jun 1966 (Box 4)
  - Science Association of Nigeria, "Popularisation of Science in Nigeria", 13-15 Feb 1978 (Box 4)
- Printed material
  - Centre for Adult Education and Extension Services, Adult Education Department, 5-30 Jun 1978; 26-29 Sep 1977; record of proceedings of a refresher course for Adult Education supervisors, record of proceedings of a workshop on Adult Education (Box 5)
  - Institute of Adult Education, University College of Botswana, 1978; annual report, IAE Report by Nnagolo Tau (Box 5)
  - Institute of Adult Education, University of Dar es Salaam, 1971; adult education directory, "Adult Education in Tanzania" (pamphlet) (Box 5)
  - Institute of Extra-Mural Studies, 15 May 1979; report on the approach to the IEMS development project by Donovan Russell (Box 5)
  - Republic of Kenya Board of Adult Education, 1960-1970; various reports (Box 5)
  - Somali Democratic Republic National Adult Education Center
    - Annual report, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1971 (Box 5)
  - University of Botswana, Lesotho and Swaziland - Report of Seminar on National Objectives at Independence, 3 Mar - 5 Mar 1967 (Box 5)
  - University of Cape Town, Department of Extra-Mural Studies, 1966-1970; reports (Box 5)
  - University College of Addis Ababa, Extension Division, 1961-1962; 1975-1976; pamphlet, annual report (Box 5)
  - University College of Swaziland, Department of Extra-Mural Studies, 1976-1979; Triennium Development Plan (Box 5)
  - University of Lagos, Continuing Education Centre, 1 Nov - 15 Dec 1979; staff development Program (Box 5)
  - University of Lovanium Extension Program, 1961-1966; 1969-1970; printed information (Box 5)
  - University of Hong Kong, Department of Extra-Mural Studies
    - Programme, "First Ten Years" pamphlet, application for enrollment, 1963-1966; 1967 (Box 5)
    - Preliminary report, memos re proposals for Leverhulme, conference on Extra-Mural Studies, 1963-1964 (Box 5)
    - Newsletters, 1962; 1963,; 1969,; 1974 (Box 6)
    - Prospectus, 1964-1965; 1966-1967,; 1968-1969,; 1696-1970 (Box 6)
  - University of Rajasthan, Jaipur, 1965-1975; miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - University of the West Indies, Department of Extra-Mural Studies
    - Report on Adult Education; St. Lucia News, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1961-1973 (Box 6)
  - Adult Education in National Development Planning: Notes Towards an Integrated Approach, by Herbold Green, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Adult Education in Nigeria: Journal of the Nigerian National Council for Adult Education vol. 1, no. 1, 1975 (Box 6)
    See also Printed material: NNCAE.
  - Adult Education Program in Liberia (Elizabeth K. Collins) (Box 6)
  - African Adult Education: Journal of the Adult Education Association of East and Central Africa (AEAECA), News Sheet No. 1, 1967 (Box 6)
  - AAEA
    See also Journal of the AAEA, v. 1 no. 1.
    - AAEA Newsletter; People's Education Association PEA News, 1976; 1978,; 1979 (Box 6)
    - Draft Proposal for an African Training and Research Programme for Adult Education, 31 Jan 1978 (Box 6)
    - Project for training and research for environmental education through Adult Education Programmes (Box 6)
    - Project request for United Nations fund for population activities, Jul 1978 (Box 6)
  - Association des universités partiellement on entièrement de langue français, "Éducation permanente" (Box 6)
  - Botswana Adult Education Newsletter vol. 1-3 (lacks 1/1, 1/3, 3/3 and 3/4), 1979 (Box 6)
  - Centre for Management Development, Advisory Service (Box 7)
  - Department of Adult Education, University of Manchester - "Role of Broadcasting in National Development: Nigeria Case Study", Jan 1974 (Box 7)
  - Federal Ministry of Education, Lagos - "National Operational Training Seminar on Functional Literacy", 12 Jul - 24 Jul 1976 (Box 7)
  - Federal Schools Broadcasts, lessons and teacher notes (Box 7)
  - Government Printing Office, Trinidad
    - "Future of the West Indies and Guyana", 13 Mar 1963; address by Hon. Dr. Eric Williams, Prime Minister of Trinidad and Tobago (Box 7)
    - "Some Thoughts on Economic Aid to Developing Countries", 19 Feb 1963; address by Hon. Dr. Eric Williams, Prime Minister of Trinidad and Tobago (Box 7)
  - Guides to universities and states, pamphlets (Box 7)
  - H.S. I. University, Adult Education Newsletter, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Information Bulletin Concerning Programmed Learning Research in Central Africa, 1965-1966 (Box 7)
  - Institute of Adult Education, University College, Salisbury, Rhodesia, Newsletter on Adult Education in East and Central Africa (no.s 2 and 4), 1964-1965 (Box 7)
  - Journal of the AAEA, v. 1 no. 1, 1979 (Box 7)
    See also Printed material: AAEA.
  - Kenya Journal of Adult Education (some issues missing), 1971-1977 (Box 7)
  - Makerere Adult Education Journal v. 1 no. 1, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Ministry of Education Adult Education Newsletter, 1978 (Box 7)
  - "New Policy on Education in Nigeria", address by Chief A.Y. Eke, Federal Commissioner of Education (Box 7)
  - Nigerian Library Association, Northern States Division, 1973; annual conference, "Educational Role of the University Library" (M.A. Parfitt) (Box 7)
  - Nigerian National Council for Adult Education
    See also Associations: Nigerian National Council for Adult Education; Adult Education in Nigeria: Journal of the Nigerian National Council for Adult Education v. 1, no. 1
    - Report of the assessment and interviewing panel for posts of Administrative/Office Secretary and Stenographer, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Study commissioned at 5th annual conference, 1975 (Box 7)
  - "Role of Adult Education in Political Awareness" (Dr. S. Egite Oyovbaire), 30 Nov 1976; paper presented at Centre for Adult Education, Ahmadu Bello University (Box 7)
  - Swaziland International Education Centre - "What is SIEC?", 1978; college report (Box 7)
  - Symposium on Adult Education in Africa: "Adult Education in the Congo," Mgr. M. Bakole, Vice Principal, University of Lovanium (Box 7)
  - "Television Sets in Schools and Colleges", Nov 1972 (Box 7)
  - United Nations Economic Commission for Africa, Occasional Report on Education and Training for Development No. 3, 1973 (Box 7)
  - UNESCO
    - Address by Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, Director General at UNESCO, on 11th celebration of Literacy Day, 8 Sep 1976 (Box 7)
    - Educational Studies and Documents No. 5, No. 10 (Box 7)
    - Technical report on the proposed network of Educational Innovation for Development in Africa, 3 Oct 1976 (Box 7)
    - World Food Program, 20 Apr 1964 (Box 7)